[screaming]
How's it going? I have the new HO scale
Golden Gate Depot Southern Pacific
coach, lounge, diner, and observation
car. These plastic models represent the
prototype found all over the Southern
Pacific Railroad from around the 1910s
until the 1980s.
Let's start by unboxing the car. All of
the cars have the same style packaging.
The label on one end is the models label
and on the other end is the Golden Gate
Depot's information.
All boxes came with a plastic wrap
protecting the outside.
Each car is protected with a plastic
cradle wrapped in a plastic sheet.
The unboxing is straightforward and none
of the cars come with spare parts.
However, the diner does come with a
spare step detail part in case one
breaks on the model.
This isn't my first time taking this car
out of the box. As you can see, the
coupler trip pin is cut. I'll go over
that later on in the video.
A good look at the underbody detail with
some separately applied detail and some
molded parts, but overall looks really
good. And before we deep dive, let's
look at what Golden Gate Depot
manufactured and some of the history of
the prototype. Golden Gate Depot did a
great job with providing most if not all
of the paint schemes that were used on
these prototypes. This includes, but not
limited to the dark olive and SP and SP
lines, daylight, solid gray, two-tone
gray, golden state, UP yellow, up
two-tone, SP stainless with scarlet
stripe, and some of the war
advertisements for the Navy, Army, and
Marines. The SP 72 ft inner urban steel
coach was built around 1923 by the
Pullman Company. Southern Pacific wanted
to replace their aging fleet of wooden
pasture cars. Their first order was 60
coaches seating about 96 passengers
each. Some people may refer to these as
Harammans, but technically that's not
right. They are identified as suburbans
or subs. These cars were 72 ft in
length, but coupler to coupler just a
little bit over 80 ft.
From their first order in 1923 to the
last one in 1927, SP had a total of 75
Suburban cars. The suburban heavyweight
coaches were primarily used along the
San Francisco commute service throughout
its entire life, but can also be seen on
trains such as the Suntan and various
excursions. The years that each paint
scheme operated are SP Lions dark olive
from 1923 to 1946, SP dark olive 1946 to
1954, two-tone gray starting in 1954,
and solid gray in 1959 until 1985 when
these cars retired. Now, on to the
model. We are in Bakersfield, California
at the La Mesa Model Railroad Museum in
San Diego, California. Here's a close-up
view of the interior. The windows do
appear a little bubbly, better than the
Heramman run from a few years ago, but
still noticeable. I will be replacing
these windows with clear styrene in the
future. The interior is well lit and
that has capacitors in there to ensure
flicker-free operation. The end of the
car has a nice steamline connection and
air hose details. For the diaphragms,
although they are good in size, I'm sad
to see that they are not operable. I
feel that a car of this price should be
having working diaphragms.
As I mentioned before, I had to cut the
coupler trip pins because some of them
were hitting the switches from being too
low of a coupler height. The couplers
are held in a spring mechanism to allow
these cars to perform on tight radius
turns. The air hose and steamlight
connection is the piece that holds the
coupler box in place. Just like the
Haramman run, these cars roll
exceptionally well. Some of the best
rolling passenger cars ever made. Add to
that, with these cars being very
lightweight, any engine can pull
multiple of these cars with ease.
My friend over at TK Railroading on
Instagram bought a two-tone gray
version.
The white stripe and lettering looks
clean with no bleeding.
I also purchased the Fly for Navy
advertisement car. I want to say that
this car was advertised during the war.
I do know the Army Marines version were
painted postwar in 1946. They shortly
had SP lines before quickly turning into
SP at the top of the car. This car
however says fly for Navy instead of
Southern Pacific. This car has the same
issues as before with the windows and
the diaphragms except this car shows
some blue paint bleeding onto the white
on the sides.
An issue specifically with this car was
the air hose on the ends were too low
and was scraping on the track. One time
the air hose caught on a switch frog and
derailed the entire car. I bent it a bit
sideways and the problem was fixed. Onto
the diner. I like the big windows. They
really show the nicely painted interior.
I also like the steps at the end. As
mentioned before, there is a replacement
step in the box in case one gets broken
or lost. These steps are screwed in
place and not glued in, which is really
nice. The interior does bring up a
question. Was the kitchen actually red?
I would like to believe the kitchen
would be stainless steel, but all of the
photos I could find were in black and
white. If you know the color of what the
kitchen would be, either stainless steel
or it was painted, let me know in the
comments below. I would like to repaint
it in the future.
TK Railroading also bought a hamburger
grill car. This car ran on some name
trains, including the Sanwaqin Daylight.
The silver stripe and lettering looks
clean as well.
Onto the lounge, the taller windows show
the unique fully painted interior. A
neat thing Golden Gate Depot did was the
etched metal detail that are in the
windows. At first, I thought they were
decals, but upon closer inspection, it's
etched metal, similar to what Plano
sells.
I also love that Golden Gate Depot added
lamps on the table. It's such a neat
detail that most manufacturers oversee.
Onto the observation. The observation
car is well done. I love the big window
next to the door on the observation
platform.
You can better see the etch metal detail
attached to the window. The car is full
of them with this detail shown on the
smaller upper windows.
A little history about this observation.
This is a 72 TAC O TAC1 observation car
specifically lettered Central Pacific or
CP.
These were converted into diners by the
1930s. All of them. So post 1930s these
cars did not exist.
I wanted to show how the coupler spring
system works. The idea behind this
system is to extend the coupler when on
a tight radius turn to compensate for
the non-working diaphragms and to ensure
smooth operation. This system causes the
gap between the cars to spread apart
when pulling a load and is visually
unappealing. Notice how far the coupler
extends when I pull on them. On a
straight section of track, the coupler
extends far out, causing the coupler to
look crooked.
This can be clearly shown as an example.
Here I'm running the train in reverse
and notice how tight the diaphragms are
with each other. This looks really good.
In the forward direction, I'm going to
stop the video on the first two suburban
cars. The first car is pulling 11 cars.
Notice the gap between car one and two.
Going towards the end of the train, look
at the gap between cars 11 and 12. If
these coupler boxes were screwed in to
the frame, we wouldn't have this issue.
I hope this video helps you decide if
you want to get your own cars or not. As
an SP modeler that models primarily in
the Bay Area, these were a must-have.
Either this option or spend $700 each on
brass cars. I want to thank Golden Gate
Depot for finally releasing these cars
as they are a childhood dream of mine to
own. Please let me know what you think.
Do you own these models? Let me know how
you feel. I'm thinking about making a
video on replacing the windows with
styrene and maybe even adding marker
lights to one of them. Anyways, I hope
you enjoy the rest of the video and have
a great rest of your day. Take care.
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
Oh, [screaming]
[screaming]
heat.
Help.
This is
[laughter]
But this one
I think on that one.
Yeah. V2 and I assume spots.
All right.
Heat. Heat.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> There's no way over there on the other
side.
I got it. I got it.
>> Look,
I know.
>> There's adventure block.
Woo!
This is
Heat.
Yeah.
back.
Are you ready?
Heat. Heat.
[laughter]
All
right.
Yeah.
That looks like
There's nobody over there on the other
side.
I got it. I got it.
>> Look.
>> I don't mind.
>> There's a winter one.
Heat. Heat.
Hey
there.
Yeah, this is
You made it.
Okay.
Foreign speech. Foreign speech. Foreign
speech.
Heat.
You have something to say.
Yeah.
Next.